A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Logistical Services, Office Files of Robert Mayer FA1719
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Logistical Services, Office Files of Robert Mayer
1952-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Mayer, Robert A. (Robert Anthony)
Ford Foundation
FA1719
1.14 Cubic Feet 3 Hollinger boxes
Arrangement
Collections consists of one series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1952-1975
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:099.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files that Robert Mayer created during his time as Officer-in-Charge of the Ford Foundation's Logistical Services unit. Logistical Services operated within the Foundation's Division of Administration and included both a Records Services and Buildings Services department. Materials in the collection appear to chiefly relate to Mayer's responsibilities over the Records Services department as well as his involvement in the larger activities of the Division of Administration.
The collection consists of one series of staff subject files. These files contain correspondence, memos, notes, drafts, and reports that document the development of the Ford Foundation's records management and archives programs from between the 1950s and 1970s. Prominent records management related subjects that the files discuss include trips to the field offices to evaluate and assist record keeping procedures, advancement and advocacy of records retention policies, filing procedures instructions, and records storage. Prominent archives related subjects include the development of the Reports Control Center (Ford catalogued reports collection), the oral history project, and policies for internal and external access to records.
While some of the other material in the collection may have been accumulated by Mayer simply in his capacity as an officer in the Division of Administration receiving documents related to activities outside of his specific unit, other records were created through his active participation in concerns beyond Logistical Services. A notable example of the later type of material is Mayer's work on the Ford Foundation's response to the U.S. House of Representatives' Staff Report of the Subcommittee on Domestic Finance of the Committee on Banking and Currency (Patman Subcommittee Report).
Biographical / Historical
Robert A. (Anthony) Meyer built a career in administration that spanned across philanthropy, business, and the military. He worked in the Ford Foundation's Division of Administration during the 1960s and 1970s as Assistant to the Vice President and Officer-in-Charge of Logistical Services.
Mayer graduated from Fairleigh Dickinson University in 1955 with a degree in English. He then served as a Sergent in the United States Army for two years where he worked in Administration and Personnel. Before joining the Ford Foundation in 1963, he worked for the Mobil Oil Company as Program Supervisor for Service Stations in the Advertising Department.
Mayer initially joined the Ford Foundation as a Program Assistant in the Latin America Program. Then in 1964, he became a Program Associate and shortly after in 1965, he became Assistant Representative to Brazil. Mayer moved to the Division of Administration in 1967 as Assistant to the President and had his responsibilities expanded in 1968 to also become Officer-in-Charge of Logistical Services. As Officer-in-Charge of Logistical Services, Mayer oversaw both the Building Services and Records Services departments.
In 1967, Mayer earned a Master's degree in Government and International Relations from New York University.
Ford Foundation; Archives; Information retrieval; Records -- Management; Records retention; Information storage and retrieval systems; Oral history
- Subject files, 1952-1975; 1; 1.14 Cubic Feet About 3 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the subject files Robert Mayer created during his time as Officer-in-Charge of the Ford Foundation's Logistical Services. These files chiefly concern Mayer's duties overseeing the development of the records management and archives programs by the Records Services department. They contain correspondence, memos, notes, drafts, and reports that discuss topics like trips to the field offices to evaluate and assist record keeping procedures, advancement and advocacy of records retention polices, filing procedures instructions, records storage, the development of the Reports Control Center (the Ford catalogued reports collection), the development of the oral history project, and policies for internal and external access to archival records. Materials show that Meyer worked closely with Records Services Manager Robert Williams to establish and structure the Foundation's records management and archives programs.
  Other records in the series document Meyer's participation in administrative concerns outside of Logistical Services. For instance, there are files showing Meyer's role in drafting the Ford Foundation's response to the U.S. House of Representatives' Staff Report of the Subcommittee on Domestic Finance of the Committee on Banking and Currency (Patman Subcommittee Report). Then there are some documents that Meyer likely received simply because he was a member of the Division of Administration. These items are mostly reports and publications.
  - Risk management policy, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Program-Directed Investments: A Wider View of Philanthropy, 1968 March (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Insurance Report for the Ford Foundation - John Liner Associates, Inc., 1966-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Program Related Investments (PRI) information papers, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Role of Women in the Ford Foundation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Patman Subcommittee Report, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Patman Subcommittee Report, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation Building Dedication program booklet, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Fellowship Programs in Business Administration and Economics, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Travel and Study Awards Program information paper, 1967 September (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Trip to Asia and Middle East offices, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Records destruction, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Disposition of foundation assets (real and operating), 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - History - Archives development, 1960-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - IR (Information Resources) Units, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Archives, 1952-1973 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Oral History Project, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Records management - Field Offices, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
  - Records management - New York City Office, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Records Services, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Reports Control Center, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Records storage, 1964-1973 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Vital records protection, 1968-1973 (Box 3, Folder 26)